SHASHI GOWDA

Office: 2-390D, Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Home: 1 Banks St, Somerville, MA 02144 gowda@mit.edu +1 (617) 899 4295

I love building well-rounded software that is simple and pleasurable to use, yet powerful and fast. I have diverse expertise in performance engineering, programming languages and compilers, large scale symbolic systems, distributed computing, analytical databases, and UI development.

EDUCATION

2018-current

PhD Candidate in Computational Science and Engineering Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA

Thesis working title: "Staged symbolic-numeric programming". I am building high-performance Symbolic computing capabilities and domain-specific compilers. *Advisor:* Prof. Alan EDELMAN | The Julia Lab GPA: 4.7/5

B. Tech., Information Technology

2010-2014

National Institute of Technology, Surathkal, India

EXPERIENCE

2016-2018

Principal Software Engineer, Julia Computing Inc.

Led development of high-performance data science tools at various levels of detail – from text processing to distributed statistics. Built JuliaDB – a pure-julia distributed-memory alternative to pandas(+dask), spark and KDB. Supported clients in deployment of the same in high-throughput production environments.

2014-2016

Research Software Engineer, (Remote) CSAIL, MIT

Worked on a distributed computing scheduler and a distributed array implementation on top of it. Also developed many tools for pedagogical interactive visualizations which were used in the famous MIT 18.06 (Linear Algebra) course.

Summers 2010, 2011, 2012, 2014

Intern, Google Summer of Code

Worked on various web-technologies and federated-computing projects under different open source organizations – StatusNet (2010, 2011 *PHP and JS*), Sahana Eden (2012 *Python*), The Julia Language (2014 *Julia and JS*)

PUBLICATIONS

2021

High-performance symbolic-numerics via multiple dispatch

S. Gowda, Y. Ma, A. Cheli, M. Gwóźdź, V.B. Shah, A. Edelman, C. Rackauckas. ACM Communications in Computer Algebra Vol. 55 (dl.acm.org)

2021 Equ

ModelingToolkit: A Composable Graph Transformation System For Equation-Based Modeling

Y. Ma, S. Gowda, R. Anantharaman, C. Laughman, V. Shah, C. Rackauckas. preprint arXiv:2103.05244

2019

Sparsity Programming: Automated Sparsity-Aware Optimizations in Differentiable Programming

S. Gowda, Y. Ma, V. Churavy, A. Edelman, C. Rackauckas. NeurIPS Program Transformations for Machine Learning Workshop. (pdf)

SOFTWARE PORTFOLIO

I have created and maintained a number of open source software projects over the years, a longer list of notable projects can be found on my website, shashi.biz

2019-current

Symbolics.jl (at MIT) Computer algebra library with a focus on ease of use, speed, extensibility, multidimensional tensor operations, and high-performance numerical code generation. Centerpiece of my thesis work. It is heavily used in Julia's modeling and simulation ecosystems, and currently has 14 direct and 74 indirect dependents (juliahub). It is used in fields from drug discovery to ocean climatology.

2016-2018

JuliaDB A distributed-memory analytical database. Competitive with Spark, pandas (+dask) (more details in our PyData NYC 2017 presentation), and kdb. I built about 80% of the project working at every level, including indexed relational tables (IndexedTables.jl), text parser compiler (TextParse.jl), compression, distributed blob storage (MemPool.jl), parallel scheduling (Dagger.jl), distributed table operations and statistics (JuliaDB.jl). At Julia Computing, I also helped clients deploy JuliaDB in machine learning applications and achieve orders of magnitudes of speedups over systems we replaced.

2014-2016

Escher.jl/Interactive UIs I built Interact.jl – a domain specific language for interactive explanations in jupyter. Later created a publishable Functional-reactive UI framework for non-UI experts in Julia. Since maintain WebIO – a minimal framework for making UI widgets that work in Jupyter, VS Code, and over the web standalone.

SKILLS

Preferred Tools

Julia, Python, C, Scheme, Unix, vim+tmux, git

Engineering skills

Software design, performance engineering, programming languages—interpretation and compilation, distributed systems, computer algebra, reactive programming.

GRADUATE-LEVEL COURSES

Theory of Computation, Numerical Methods, Large Scale Symbolic Systems, Computational Classical Mechanics, Statistical Learning Theory, Autonomy and Decision Making.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Spring 2019 & Fall 2020 Introduction to computational thinking (18.S191)

Fall 2018 High-performance computing (18.337)

NOTABLE TALKS

2022 Strange Loop, St Louis. "Symbolic-numeric programming in Julia"

SciMLCon, Boston, MA "Symbolic arrays: past, present and future"

JuliaCon, London, UK "How JuliaDB works"

NeurIPS, Workshop on Programming languages for ML, Vancouver BC "Sparsity aware optimizations in differentiable programming"

PyData NYC, NYC "JuliaDB: A data system for Julia (with Jeff

Bezanson and Josh Day)"

2016 Microsoft, Bangalore "Keynote: A Functional Algebra of UIs"

JuliaCon, Boston, MA "Escher.jl-a new way to make and deploy UIs"